In many patriarchal societies and tribal societies,
في العديد من المجتمعات الذكورية والقبلية
fathers are usually known by their sons,
يُعرف الأباء عادة نسبة لأبنائهم
but I'm one of the few fathers
ولكني واحد من القلائل
who is known by his daughter,
الذين يعرفون نسية لابنتهم
and I am proud of it.
وأنا فخور بهذا الشيء
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Malala started her campaign for education
بدأت ملالا حملتها من أجل التعليم
and stood for her rights in 2007,
والدفاع عن حقوقها، في عام 2007
and when her efforts were honored in 2011,
وعندما كُرمت من أجل جهودها في عام 2011
and she was given the national youth peace prize,
ومُنِحَت الجائزة الوطنية للسلام
and she became a very famous,
أصبحت مشهورة جدًا
very popular young girl of her country.
أصبحت معروفة جدًا في دولتها
Before that, she was my daughter,
قبل كل ذلك، كانت ابنتي
but now I am her father.
ولكن الآن، أنا أبوها
Ladies and gentlemen,
سيداتي وسادتي
if we glance to human history,
إذا نظرنا لتاريخ البشرية،
the story of women
قصة النساء
is the story of injustice,
هي قصة ظلم،
inequality,
عدم مساواة،
violence and exploitation.
عنف واستغلال.
You see,
كما ترون،
in patriarchal societies,
في المجتمعات الذكورية،
right from the very beginning,
من البداية،
when a girl is born,
عندما تولد بنت،
her birth is not celebrated.
ولادتها لا يحتفل بها.
She is not welcomed,
وهي غير مرحب فيها،
neither by father nor by mother.
سواء من أمها أو من أبيها.
The neighborhood comes
الجيران يأتون
and commiserates with the mother,
يواسون الأم،
and nobody congratulates the father.
ولا يباركون للأب.
And a mother is very uncomfortable
الأم تكون غير مرتاحة جدًا
for having a girl child.
لولادتها لبنت.
When she gives birth to the first girl child,
عندما تولد الفتاة الأولى،
first daughter, she is sad.
الابنة الأولى، تكون الأم حزينة جدًا.
When she gives birth to the second daughter,
عندما تولد الابنة الثانية،
she is shocked,
تُصدم الأم،
and in the expectation of a son,
وعندما تكون متوقعة أن يولد ابن ذكر،
when she gives birth to a third daughter,
ولكن تولد فتاة ثالثة،
she feels guilty like a criminal.
تشعر الأم بالذنب وكأنها مجرمة.
Not only the mother suffers,
ليست الأم فقط هي من تعاني،
but the daughter, the newly born daughter,
بل وأيضا الفتاة، المولودة الجديدة،
when she grows old,
عندما تكبر،
she suffers too.
تعاني هي أيضا.
At the age of five,
في عمر الخامسة،
while she should be going to school,
عندما يجب أن تكون في المدرسة،
she stays at home
تبقى الفتاة في البيت
and her brothers are admitted in a school.
بينما يذهب إخوتها الذكور إلى المدرسة.
Until the age of 12, somehow,
وحتى الثانية عشر من عمرها، بطريقة ما،
she has a good life.
تعيش حياة جيدة.
She can have fun.
تستطيع أن تمرح.
She can play with her friends in the streets,
تستطيع أن تلعب مع صديقاتها في الشوارع،
and she can move around in the streets
وأن تتنقل في الشوارع
like a butterfly.
مثل الفراشة.
But when she enters her teens,
ولكن عندما تصبح مراهقة،
when she becomes 13 years old,
عندما تدخل عأمها الثالث عشر،
she is forbidden to go out of her home
تُمنع من مغادرة البيت
without a male escort.
من دون مرافق.
She is confined under the four walls of her home.
تسجن بين أربع جدران بيتها.
She is no more a free individual.
هي ليست فردا حرا بعد الآن.
She becomes the so-called honor
تصبح بما يسمى بالشرف
of her father and of her brothers
شرف أبيها وإخوتها
and of her family,
وعائلتها.
and if she transgresses
وإذا تعدت
the code of that so-called honor,
حدود ذلك الشرف،
she could even be killed.
قد تُقتل.
And it is also interesting that this so-called
ومن المثير للاهتمام أن ميثاق الشرف
code of honor,
المزعوم،
it does not only affect the life of a girl,
لا يؤثر فقط على حياة الفتاة،
it also affects the life
بل يؤثر أيضا على حياة
of the male members of the family.
الذكور في عائلتها.
I know a family of seven sisters and one brother,
أعرف عائلة مكونة من سبع أخوات وأخ واحد،
and that one brother,
وذلك الأخ الواحد،
he has migrated to the Gulf countries,
هاجر إلى دول الخليج،
to earn a living for his seven sisters
لكي يكسب المعيشة من أجل أخواته السبع
and parents,
وأمه وأبيه،
because he thinks that it will be humiliating
لأنه يعتقد أنه سيكون من المهين
if his seven sisters learn a skill
إذا تعلمت أخواته السبع مهارة
and they go out of the home
وخرجن من البيت
and earn some livelihood.
لكي يكسبن المعيشة بنفسهن.
So this brother,
هذا الأخ،
he sacrifices the joys of his life
ضحى بمتعة حياته
and the happiness of his sisters
وبسعادة أخواته
at the altar of so-called honor.
من أجل ما يسمى بالشرف.
And there is one more norm
وهنالك عادة أخرى
of the patriarchal societies
في المجتمعات الذكورية
that is called obedience.
تسمى بالإطاعة.
A good girl is supposed to be
"الفتاة الجيدة" من المفروض أن تكون
very quiet, very humble
هادئة جدًا ومتواضعة جدًا
and very submissive.
ومطيعة جدًا.
It is the criteria.
هذا هو المعيار.
The role model good girl should be very quiet.
يجب أن تكون الفتاة الجيدة المُقتدى بها هادئة جدا.
She is supposed to be silent
من المفروض أن تكون صامتة
and she is supposed to accept the decisions
وأن تفبل قرارات
of her father and mother
أبيها وأمها
and the decisions of elders,
وقرارت الأكبر منها سنًا،
even if she does not like them.
حتى لو لم تعجبها.
If she is married to a man she doesn't like
إذا كانت متزوجة من رجل لا تحبه
or if she is married to an old man,
أو من رجل كبير في السن،
she has to accept,
عليها أن تقبل بذلك،
because she does not want to be dubbed
لانها لا تريد أن ينظر إليها على أنها
as disobedient.
"غير مطيعة".
If she is married very early,
إذا تزوجت في سن صغيرة جدًا،
she has to accept.
عليها أن تقبل بذلك.
Otherwise, she will be called disobedient.
وإلا سوف ينادونها بغير مطيعة.
And what happens at the end?
وماذا يحدث بالنهاية؟
In the words of a poetess,
في كلمات الشاعرة،
she is wedded, bedded,
هي تُزوّج، توضع في السرير
and then she gives birth to more sons and daughters.
وبعد ذلك تلِد المزيد من الأبناء والبنات.
And it is the irony of the situation
وسخرية الوضع
that this mother,
أن هذه الأم،
she teaches the same lesson of obedience
ستعلم نفس درس الاطاعة
to her daughter
لابنتها
and the same lesson of honor to her sons.
ونفس درس الشرف لأبنائها.
And this vicious cycle goes on, goes on.
وهذه الحلقة االمفرغة تطول وتطول.
Ladies and gentlemen,
سيداتي وسادتي
this plight of millions of women
وضع الملايين من النساء
could be changed
يمكن أن يُغَيّر
if we think differently,
إذا فكرنا بطريقة مختلفة،
if women and men think differently,
إذا فكر النساء والرجال بطريقة مختلفة،
if men and women in the tribal and patriarchal societies
إذا النساء والرجال في المجتمعات الذكورية والقبلية
in the developing countries,
في الدول المتطورة،
if they can break a few norms
إذا استطاعوا أن يكسروا بعض عادات
of family and society,
العائلة والمجتمع،
if they can abolish the discriminatory laws
إذا كان بامكانهم إلغاء القوانين العنصرية
of the systems in their states,
في الأنظمة في دولهم،
which go against the basic human rights
التي تتعارض مع حقوق الإنسان الأساسية
of the women.
للنساء.
Dear brothers and sisters, when Malala was born,
أيها الإخوة والأخوات، عندما ولدت ملالا،
and for the first time,
وللمرة الأولى,
believe me,
صدقوني,
I don't like newborn children, to be honest,
أنا لا أحب المواليد الجدد، سأكون صادقًا معكم,
but when I went and I looked into her eyes,
ولكن عندما نظرت في عينيها
believe me,
صدقوني،
I got extremely honored.
حصلت على شرف كبير.
And long before she was born,
وقبل أن تولد بفترة طويلة،
I thought about her name,
فكرت بإسمها،
and I was fascinated with a heroic
وكنت مفتونا بمناضلة
legendary freedom fighter in Afghanistan.
أسطورية بطولية في أفغانستان.
Her name was Malalai of Maiwand,
اسمها كان مالالاي من مايواند،
and I named my daughter after her.
أسميت ابنتي تيمنا بها.
A few days after Malala was born,
أيام قليلة بعد أن ولدت ملالا،
my daughter was born,
وُلِدَت ابنتي
my cousin came --
أتى ابن عمي -
and it was a coincidence --
وكانت صدفة -
he came to my home
أتى إلى منزلي
and he brought a family tree,
وأحضر شجرة العائلة،
a family tree of the Yousafzai family,
شجرة عائلة يوسفازي،
and when I looked at the family tree,
نظرت إلى الشجرة،
it traced back to 300 years of our ancestors.
ورأيت أنها تتعقب تاريخ 300 سنة من أسلافنا.
But when I looked, all were men,
ولكن كانوا كلهم رجالا،
and I picked my pen,
فالتقطت قلمي،
drew a line from my name,
أضفت خطًا لاسمي،
and wrote, "Malala."
وكتبت "ملالا".
And when she grow old,
وعندما كبرت،
when she was four and a half years old,
وأصبح عمرها أربع أعوام ونصف،
I admitted her in my school.
سجلتها في مدرستي.
You will be asking, then, why should I mention about
لربما تتساءلون لماذا أذكر
the admission of a girl in a school?
أني سجلتها في مدرسة؟
Yes, I must mention it.
يجب أن أذكر هذا الشيء.
It may be taken for granted in Canada,
ربما يكون هذا الشيء مفهوم ضمنيًا في كندا،
in America, in many developed countries,
وفي أمريكا وفي العديد من الدول المتقدمة
but in poor countries,
ولكن في البلدان الفقيرة،
in patriarchal societies, in tribal societies,
في المجتمعات الذكورية والمجتمعات القبلية،
it's a big event for the life of girl.
هذا الشيء يعتبر حدثا هامًا في حياة البنت.
Enrollment in a school means
الالتحاق بالمدرسة يعني
recognition of her identity and her name.
أن تعرف هويتها واسمها.
Admission in a school means
القبول في المدرسة يعني
that she has entered the world of dreams
أنها قد دخلت عالم الأحلام
and aspirations
وعالم الأمال
where she can explore her potentials
حيث يمكنها أن تكتشف قواها الكامنة
for her future life.
في حياتها المستقبلية.
I have five sisters,
لدي خمسة أخوات،
and none of them could go to school,
لم تتمكن أي واحدة منهن أن تلتحق بالمدرسة،
and you will be astonished,
ولكنكم سوف تتفاجؤون.
two weeks before,
أنه من أسبوعين،
when I was filling out the Canadian visa form,
عندما كنت أملأ طلب الفيزا الكندية،
and I was filling out the family part of the form,
عندما كنت أملأ القسم المتعلق بالعائلة من الطلب،
I could not recall
لم أستطع أن أتذكر
the surnames of some of my sisters.
الأسماء الأخيرة لبعض أخواتي.
And the reason was
والسبب وراء ذلك
that I have never, never seen the names
هو أنني لم أر في حياتي كلها
of my sisters written on any document.
أسماءهن مكتوبة في وثيقة ما
That was the reason that
كان هذا هو السبب الذي دعاني
I valued my daughter.
إلى أن أقدر ابنتي.
What my father could not give to my sisters
الشيء الذي لم يتمكن والدي من منحه لأخواتي
and to his daughters,
أي بناته،
I thought I must change it.
كنت أعتقد أنه لا بد أن أغيره.
I used to appreciate the intelligence
لطالما قدرت الذكاء
and the brilliance of my daughter.
والفطنة الذين تمتلكهما ابنتي.
I encouraged her to sit with me
كنت أشجعها أن تجلس معي
when my friends used to come.
عندما كان أصدقائي يأتون.
I encouraged her to go with me to different meetings.
كنت أشجعها أن تذهب معي إلى العديد من الاجتماعات.
And all these good values,
وكل هذه القيم الطيبة،
I tried to inculcate in her personality.
التي كنت أحوال غرسها في شخصيتها.
And this was not only she, only Malala.
لم تكن لها فقط. لملالا فقط.
I imparted all these good values
لقد نقلت كل هذه القيم الطيبة
to my school, girl students and boy students as well.
لطلاب مدرستي من الفتيات والفتيان على حد سواء
I used education for emancipation.
استخدمت التعليم كوسيلة للتحرير.
I taught my girls,
علمت طالباتي،
I taught my girl students,
علمت طالباتي من الفتيات،
to unlearn the lesson of obedience.
ألّا يتعلمن درس الإطاعة.
I taught my boy students
علمت طلابي من الفتيان
to unlearn the lesson of so-called pseudo-honor.
ألّا يتعلموا الدرس الذي يسمى بالشرف المزيف.
Dear brothers and sisters,
إخوتي وأخواتي الأعزاء،
we were striving for more rights for women,
لقد كنا نسعى من أجل حقوق إضافية للمرأة
and we were struggling to have more,
وكنا نكافح كي نحصل على المزيد،
more and more space for the women in society.
المزيد من المساحة للنساء في المجتمع.
But we came across a new phenomenon.
ولكن ظهرت أمامنا ظاهرة جديدة.
It was lethal to human rights
كانت قاتلة لحقوق الإنسان
and particularly to women's rights.
وبالتحديد لحقوق المرأة.
It was called Talibanization.
كانت تسمى بالـ"الطلبنة".
It means a complete negation
والتي تعني استبعادًا تامًا
of women's participation
لمشاركة المرأة
in all political, economical and social activities.
في كل الأنشطة السياسية والاقتصادية والاجتماعية
Hundreds of schools were lost.
مئات المدارس فجرت.
Girls were prohibited from going to school.
منعت الفتيات من الذهاب إلى المدرسة.
Women were forced to wear veils
وأجبرت النساء على لبس الخمار
and they were stopped from going to the markets.
ولم يسمح لهن الذهاب إلى الأسواق.
Musicians were silenced,
أُسكت الموسيقيون،
girls were flogged
جلدت الفتيات
and singers were killed.
والمغنون قتلوا.
Millions were suffering,
الملايين كانوا يعانون،
but few spoke,
ولكن القليلون هم من تحدثوا،
and it was the most scary thing
وقد كان أكثر الأشياء رعبًا
when you have all around such people
أن تكون محاطًا بأشخاص كهؤلاء
who kill and who flog,
ممن يقتلون ويجلدون،
and you speak for your rights.
وأن تكون أنت تتحدث عن حقوقك.
It's really the most scary thing.
لقد كان حقًا أكثر الأشياء رعبًا.
At the age of 10,
في عمر الـ10 سنوات،
Malala stood, and she stood for the right
وقفت ملالا، لقد وقفت
of education.
من أجل الحق في التعليم
She wrote a diary for the BBC blog,
لقد كتبت ملاحظة من أجل مدونة الـBBC،
she volunteered herself
لقد تطوعت بنفسها
for the New York Times documentaries,
من أجل أفلام وثائقية للـنيويورك تايمز
and she spoke from every platform she could.
لقد تحدثت من كل منصة تمكنت من الحديث عليها.
And her voice was the most powerful voice.
وكان صوتها الصوت الأكثر قوة.
It spread like a crescendo all around the world.
لقد انتشر دوي صوتها في كل العالم.
And that was the reason the Taliban
وكان هذا هو السبب الذي جعل حركة طالبان
could not tolerate her campaign,
غير قادرة على تحمل حملتها،
and on October 9 2012,
في التاسع من أكتوبر عام 2012،
she was shot in the head at point blank range.
أطللقت على رأسها النار من مسافة قريبة.
It was a doomsday for my family and for me.
كان هذا اليوم كأنه يوم القيامة بالنسبة لعائلتي ولي.
The world turned into a big black hole.
تحول العالم إلى ثقب أسود كبير.
While my daughter was
عندما كانت طفلتي
on the verge of life and death,
بين الحياة والموت،
I whispered into the ears of my wife,
همست في أذن زوجتي،
"Should I be blamed for what happened
"هل ألام على ما حصل
to my daughter and your daughter?"
لابنتي وابنتك؟"
And she abruptly told me,
ولكنها وبشكل مفاجئ قالت
"Please don't blame yourself.
"أرجوك لا تلم نفسك.
You stood for the right cause.
لقد وقفت في جانب الحق.
You put your life at stake
لقد وضعت حياتك على المحك
for the cause of truth,
من أجل الحق،
for the cause of peace,
من أجل السلام،
and for the cause of education,
من أجل التعليم،
and your daughter in inspired from you
لقد أُلهمت ابنتك منك
and she joined you.
وانضمت إليك.
You both were on the right path
كلاكما كان على الطريق الصحيح
and God will protect her."
والله سوف يحميها".
These few words meant a lot to me,
هذه الكلمات القليلة عنت الكثير لي،
and I didn't ask this question again.
ولم أسأل هذا السؤال مجددًا.
When Malala was in the hospital,
عندما كانت ملالا في المستشفى،
and she was going through the severe pains
كانت تقاسى شديد الالأم
and she had had severe headaches
وتعاني من صداع شديد
because her facial nerve was cut down,
لأن عصبها الوجهي قُطع،
I used to see a dark shadow
لقد كنت أرى ظلًا قاتمًا
spreading on the face of my wife.
يخيم على وجه زوجتي.
But my daughter never complained.
ولكن ابنتي لم تتذمر يومًا.
She used to tell us,
كانت تقول لنا،
"I'm fine with my crooked smile
"إنني بخير مع ابتسامتى المعوجة
and with my numbness in my face.
وشعور التنميل في وجهي
I'll be okay. Please don't worry."
سأكون على ما يرام، رجاء لا تقلقوا".
She was a solace for us,
كانت هي عزائنا وسلواننا،
and she consoled us.
وقامت بمواساتنا.
Dear brothers and sisters,
إخوتي وأخواتي الأعزاء،
we learned from her how to be resilient
علمتنا المرونة
in the most difficult times,
في أقسى الأواقات،
and I'm glad to share with you
أنا سعيد بمشاركتي إياكم
that despite being an icon
أنه بالرغم من أنها رمز
for the rights of children and women,
لحقوق الطفل والمرأة،
she is like any 16-year old girl.
هي مثل أي فتاة بعمر الـ16 عام.
She cries when her homework is incomplete.
تبكي عندما لا تكمل واجبها المنزلي.
She quarrels with her brothers,
تتخاصم مع إخوتها،
and I am very happy for that.
وأنا سعيد جدًا لذلك.
People ask me,
يسألني الناس،
what special is in my mentorship
ما هو الشيء المميز في تربيتي
which has made Malala so bold
الذي جعل ملالا جريئة وشجاعة جدًا
and so courageous and so vocal and poised?
والذي جعلها تتحدث وتكون متوازنة؟
I tell them, don't ask me what I did.
وأجيبهم، لا تسألوني ماذا فعلت.
Ask me what I did not do.
ولكن اسألوني ماذا لم أفعل.
I did not clip her wings, and that's all.
أنا لم أقصص أجنحتها. هذا كل ما في الأمر.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you very much. Thank you. (Applause)
شكرًا، شكرًا لكم جزيلًا، شكرًا لكم. (تصفيق)